Guide to the Washington Square Park Redevelopment Collection 1952-1966 MS 678
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Washington Square Park Redevelopment Collection
1952-1966
MS 678
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.63 Linear feet (1 box)
This is a collection of records of various community organizations fighting the redevelopment of Washington Square Park and the surrounding area. Their efforts included closing the park to traffic, fighting the construction of NYU's library and university housing, and the creation of more parkland. The collection contains letters and statements of opposition from local community groups and individuals. Also included are government documents and New York University publications relating to the potential redevelopment.
Custodial History note
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) See guidelines in Reading room for details.
Historical Note
1952 New York University announces plans to redevelop Washington Square Park Southeast area.
1954 Washington Square Park Committee announces its plan to fight the project.
1958 Washington Square Park converts from being open to all traffic to only being open to bus traffic.
1959 Washington Square Park completely closed to traffic.
1964 New York University reveals design of library on Washington Square South.
1965 New York University asks the City Planning Commission to review proposal of campus expansion, including the library.
1966 Community Planning Commission holds public hearing on the project.
1973 New York University's Bobst Library completed.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is comprised of materials relating to Washington Square Park's history from 1952 to 1966. The issues that these papers cover are the traffic through the square, New York University's new library and housing project, parkland and park use. The collection consists of letters and statements of opposition, community organizations' records opposing the redevelopment, government documents and New York University publications. Also included are letters to Shirley Hayes, a local community leader who was instrumental in getting the park closed to traffic.
Arrangement
Most of the collection is arranged by organization. The letters from individuals and to Shirley Hayes are arranged chronologically. The papers are arranged into the following series:
Series I: Community Organizations
Series II: New York University Publications
Series III: Government Documents
Series IV: Letters and Statements of Opposition
Series V: Other Material
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Further material on Washington Square Park can be found in the Records of the Washington Arch and in the Shirley Hayes Papers.
Abrams, Charles, 1902-1970; Association of Village Home-Owners; Community Planning Board #2; Dean, Jr., Sidney, W.; Greenwich Village Association; Hayes, Shirley, 1921-2001; Koch, Ed, 1924-; Lower West Side Civic League; New York University; Save Our Square Committee; Washington Square Neighbors; Washington Square Park Committee; Wittenburg, Ruth; City Planning; Discrimination in housing; Greenwich Village (New York, NY); Housing; Land use, urban; Washington Square Park (New York, NY)
- Series I: Community Organizations, 1953-1966
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains a variety of materials from various community organizations that supported the Washington Square Park and Greenwich Village community. Most of these community organizations supported the closing of the park to traffic and not building the New York University library. Materials include newsletters, letters, minutes, reports, petitions, and meeting flyers.
  - Association of Village Home-Owners, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Community Planning Board #2, 1965-1966, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Greenwich Village Association, 1953, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lower West Side Civic League, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Save Our Square Committee, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Washington Square Park Neighbors, 1954-1955, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Washington Square Park Committee, 1954, 1958, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Other Community Organizations, 1953-1966, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: New York University Publications, 1952-1966
  This series contains publications produced by New York University. The materials included are chancellor's reports, student newspapers, newsletters, reports, a map, and newspapers clippings. This part of the collection gives the university's prospective on their projects.
  - Materials Regarding Redevelopment of Washington Square Park, 1952-1966, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series III: Government Documents, 1956-1966
  This series contains documents from New York City agencies and New York State agencies. The materials included are letters from the agencies, reports, meeting minutes, calendars, and law amendments. The letters show what individual members of the local government thought about the projects.
  - City Planning Commission, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Manhattan Borough President's Office, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - City of New York Publications, 1956, 1958, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - State of New York Publications, 1957, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Letters and Statements of Opposition, 1953-1966
  This series contains letters and statements of opposition from individuals, mostly from the Greenwich Village and Washington Square Park areas. It also includes letters written to Shirley Hayes. Hayes was influential in getting the park closed to traffic.
  - Letters and Statements Regarding Development, 1953-1966, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Shirley Hayes, 1953, 1966, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series V: Other Material, 1953-1966
  This series contains newspaper clippings, notes, and a map. The clippings do not include New York University newspapers. It is unclear who took the notes, but they do provide information on the redevelopment of the square. The map is of the proposed street changes to what was then known as West Broadway (La Guardia Place now).
  - Clippings, 1952-1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Map, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)